http://youtu.be/R7RFjNFycyU
http://youtu.be/R7RFjNFycyU
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Because the focus of this class will be on I/O,
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Bởi vì lớp này sẽ học kỹ về I/O,
let's look, let's overview the type of I/O on our TM4C123.
nên hãy xem I/O trên con TM4C123.
We have a Cortex M4 processor.
Ta có vi xử lý Cortex M4.
And we have RAM.
RAM
And on another bus, we have ROM.
và 1 bus khác, nối với ROM.
But let's look at the I/O devices.
Hãy chú ý I/O.
The Cortex M has ports.
Cortex M có 1 số port.
And they're labeled port A, port B, port C, port D--
Gọi là port A, port B, port C, port D--
there's a lot of them.
rất nhiều.
It's really important--
Thứ quan trọng là
port E, and port F. OK.
port E và port F. Được rồi.
And the idea of a port-- and again, they're all connected up here on the
Những port này đều sẽ được kết nối
system bus so that the processor of your programs can access these ports.
vào bus hệ thống để vi xử lý có thể truy xuất được.
And each of these ports have pins.
Những port này sẽ có pin.
Like, port A has got eight pins--
Như port A sẽ có 8 pin
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Port B has got eight.
Port B cũng có 8.
And we'll draw it this way, a bit quicker.
Ta vẽ thế này, sẽ nhanh hơn.
Port E has six.
Port E có 6.
Port F has five.
Port F có 5.
Port D has eight.
Port D có 8.
And port C is special.
Port C hơi đặc biệt chút.
We're going to have access to four.
Ta truy xuất được 4.
Let me be the first to tell you to not to attach to PC3, PC2, PC1, and PC0.
Bạn đừng đụng tới PC3, PC2, PC1, và PC0.
Those we're going to reserve for our debugger, so don't touch those.
Mấy chân này để dành cho debugger, đừng đụng tới.
Leave those alone.
Để qua 1 bên.
You'll be happier.
Sẽ tốt hơn cho mọi người.
Let's look at the types of I/O we have.
Hãy chú ý loại của I/O.
We have parallel, which means that, all at once, we can set all six bits
Ta có loại song song, nghĩa là ta có thể set 6 bit
of this port E all at once.
của port E cùng 1 lúc.
Then, we have serial I/O. And we'll see a couple of types of serial I/O.
Ngoài ra ta có I/O tuần tự. Có 1 vài loại I/O tuần tự khác nhau.
And this allows us to send one bit at a time.
Cho phép ta gửi 1 bit mỗi lúc.
I'll make the analogy of how do you send Morse code.
Bạn còn nhớ mã Morse.
You've all played this game before [voice is wrong, should be]--
Tất cả chúng ta đều đã chơi trước đây [1 vài bạn có thể chưa biết]
short, short, short, pause, long, long, long, pause,
tít, tít, tít, ngừng, te, te, te, ngừng,
short, short, short.
tít, tít, tít.
That is code for SOS--
Đó là tín hiệu SOS.
save our ship.
cứu tôi với.
So serial I/O will be used to communicate with other devices or
I/O tuần tự được dùng để giao tiếp thiết bị khác hoặc
other computers.
hoặc máy tính khác.
Very important for communication.
Kiểu giao tiếp này rất quan trọng.
We have other types of I/O. We have analog I/O. Analog I/O can be either
Ta có loại I/O khác nữa. Là I/O analog. I/O analog có thể
an input to measure what goes on in the external world, or it could be an
là input để đo lường một giá trị bên ngoài, hoặc có thể là
output to generate signals like sound or motion.
output để xuất tín hiệu, như âm thanh hoặc chuyển động.
And the third very important type of I/O that we will do is time.
Có 1 loại I/O rất quan trọng, đó là thời gian.
Time can be measured as an input.
Thời gian có thể được đo như input.
And time can also be produced as an output, to
Và cũng có thể được xuất ra như output,
generate pulses and signals.
cho xung hay tín hiệu.
So time, as we saw, is an important aspect of embedded systems, and
Cho nên, thời gian, như ta sẽ thấy, là 1 yếu tố quan trọng của những hệ thống nhúng, và
therefore, an important aspect of I/O that we will produce.
do đó, là 1 thành phần quan trọng của I/O mà ta sẽ xuất ra.
OK.
Được rồi.
Now what I want to do is to focus on this part.
Tiếp theo, ta sẽ chú ý phần này.
This is a microcontroller because it contains an entire computer, including
Nó là vi điều khiển vì nó là 1 máy tính hoàn chỉnh, bao gồm
the I/O, including the pins for the I/O. And let me show you the one we're
I/O, kế cả pin cho I/O. Và để tôi cho bạn thấy 1 vi xử lý
going to use in this class.
sẽ được dùng trong lớp này.
All right, I'd like to show you the microcontroller we're going to use in
Tôi sẽ cho bạn thấy vi điềi khiển ta sẽ dùng
this class.
trong lớp này.
This big chip here in the center of this board is the TM4C123.
Con chip to nằm ở giữa board là TM4C123.
And it is a microcontroller.
Nó là 1 vi điều khiển.
The pins that I described in the previous slide are those wires coming
Những pin mà tôi nói trong slide trước là những dây
out of this chip.
chạy ra khỏi chip.
So this is the microcontroller.
Cho nên đây là vi điều khiển.
And this is a board which we will use to develop code for that
Và đây là board ta dùng để viết code cho
microcontroller.
vi điều khiển đó.